Eric J. Earley

ericearley@u.northwestern.edu 312-238-2079

SUMMARY

PhD candidate in Biomedical Engineering at Northwestern University. My research merges two traditionally separate fields: control of robotic prosthetic limbs and motor learning and adaptation. My work aims to better understand how the prosthesis and the user communicate back and forth, and how to improve this communication loop to refine a user's fine control over the prosthetic limb.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Biomedical Engineering	2014 – 2019 (expected)	Northwestern University
M.S. Biomedical Engineering	2012-2014	Northwestern University
B.S. Engineering: Mechanical Specialty	2008 – 2012	Colorado School of Mines

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Doctoral Research 2014 – 2019 (expected)

Northwestern University ◆ Shirley Ryan AbilityLab

Center for Bionic Medicine ◆ Neural Engineering for Prosthetics and Orthotics

Advisor: Dr. Levi Hargrove

Using sensory feedback to improve motor adaptation by providing information not accurately available via vision, as determined by psychophysical analysis.

Master's Research 2012 – 2014

Northwestern University ◆ Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago

Center for Bionic Medicine ◆ Neural Engineering for Prosthetics and Orthotics

Advisor: Dr. Levi Hargrove

Improved control of partial-hand prostheses through optimization of EMG pattern-recognition parameters while preserving wrist mobility.

Volunteer Internship 2012

University of Colorado • Anschutz Medical Campus

BioMechatronics Development Laboratory

Advisor: Dr. Richard F. ff Weir

Designed thumb actuation mechanism and housing and created SolidWorks models of prototype 3-DOF prosthetic hand.

Undergraduate Senior Design

2011 - 2012

Colorado School of Mines

Advisor: Dr. Cynthia Norrgran

Outfitted powered standing wheelchair with EEG intent recognition control.

Summer Internship 2011

ADA Technologies, Inc.

Supervisor: Dr. Thierry Carriere

Developed and tested robotic fire detection and targeted fire suppression system for use in an aircraft dry bay.

Eric J. Earley Page | 2

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Publications

• E.J. Earley, L.J. Hargrove, T.A. Kuiken, "Dual Window Pattern Recognition Classifier for Improved Partial-Hand Prosthesis Control," *Frontiers in Neuroscience*, vol. 10, no. 58, 2016. doi:10.3389/fnins.2016.00058.

Conference Papers and Posters

- E.J. Earley, K.J. Kaveny, R.E. Johnson, L.J. Hargrove and J.W. Sensinger, "Joint-based velocity feedback improves myoelectric prosthesis performance," 2017 Myoelectric Controls and Upper Limb Prosthetics Symposium, pp. 116, 2017.
- E.J. Earley, K.J. Kaveny, R.E. Johnson, L.J. Hargrove and J.W. Sensinger, "Joint-based velocity feedback to virtual limb dynamic perturbations," 2017 International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR), pp. 1313-1318, 2017. doi: 10.1109/ICORR.2017.8009430.
- ◆ E.J. Earley and L.J. Hargrove, "The Effect of Wrist Position and Hand-Grasp Pattern on Virtual Prosthesis Task Performance," 6th IEEE RAS/EMBS International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob), pp. 542-547, 2016. doi: 10.1109/BIOROB.2016.7523682.
- ◆ E.J. Earley, A.A. Adewuyi, and L.J. Hargrove, "Optimizing Pattern Recognition-Based Control for Partial-Hand Prosthesis Application," *Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE*, pp. 3574-3577, 2014. doi: 10.1109/EMBC.2014.6944395.

Journal Referee

- IEEE Transactions on Neural Systems & Rehabilitation Engineering
- Biomedical Signal Processing and Control
- IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference
- PLOS ONE
- Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering
- Assistive Technology
- ♦ Allied Academies Biomedical Research
- IEEE International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics
- Myoelectric Control Conference
- **♦** Transactions on Mechatronics
- ♦ Transactions on Human-Machine Systems
- IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics

ACADEMIC & TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Pattern recognition, classification, and machine learning algorithms
- Human motor control, motor learning and adaptation, musculoskeletal anatomy
- ♦ MATLAB, Simulink, LabVIEW
- ◆ SolidWorks, FEA
- ♦ HTML5, CSS
- Adobe Audition, Photoshop, Premiere, After Effects

LEADERSHIP

National Communicating Science Conference

2017 – *present*

Program Organizing Committee

Program organizer for sixth annual national conference held summer 2018. Selected panelists and organized non-panel workshops.

Chicago Communicating Science Conference

2015 - 2017

Treasurer, Lead Organizer

Organizer and treasurer for second conference held summer 2016. Lead organizer for third conference held summer 2017. Tracked budget and donated funds, secured conference location, and oversaw the conference.

Eric J. Earley Page | 3

Northwestern University McCormick Graduate Leadership Council

2013 – *present*

Workshop Coordinator and Instructor

Coordinated workshops to teach introductory through advanced MATLAB and SolidWorks skills, and coordinated additional workshops on other transferable skills, for over 600 graduate students.

Northwestern University Biomedical Engineering Graduate Students Group

2013 - 2017

Co-President

Oversaw periodic academic and social events, maintained communication with other officers, proposed and facilitated changes to annual BME research day including pop talks (short 3-minute overviews of research using jargon-free language), and rebuilt website.

Alpha Phi Omega Co-Ed Service Fraternity

2010 - 2012

Treasurer

Minimum 15 hours of community service per semester. Collected and managed dues and reimbursements for \$3000 annual budget.

Colorado School of Mines Robotics Club

2008 - 2011

Treasurer, Mentor

Developed and managed \$26,000 annual budget. Co-initiated project to design, build and program self-balancing wheelchair. Mentored high school students for FIRST Robotics Competition

PUBLIC OUTREACH & EDUCATION

Sci-Inspiration YouTube Channel

2018

Channel explores scientific topics through popular media including movies, television, and video games.

• Why can't we travel Faster than Light?: Explores the laws of physics that prevent traveling faster than the speed of light

Other Science Videos

2016 – present

- "STEM Connect Careers: Eric Earley." *Discovery Education*, 2017.
- Prosthetic Limbs and Motor Adaptation: A short 3-minute video explaining the purpose of my research using clear and concise language

Science Writing

2017 – present

• <u>The Cybathlon: The Olympics of Restoring Daily Tasks</u>, HELIX Magazine.

Public Talks & Demos

2014 – present

- "Neural Engineering: Designing Bionic Limbs Controlled by the Brain," College of DuPage STEMinar Series, 2018.
- "Get-A-Grip" Program, Nettelhorst Elementary, 2017 present
- Chicago Science Festival, Illinois Science Council, 2016 present
- Museum of Science and Industry Robotics Week, 2016 present
- "ProsthEthics", guest lecture for Robot Ethics course at University of Notre Dame, 2016 present
- "How Do I Talk to my Robo-Limb?", RSG Science Communicating Workshop, 2016.
- Engineer's Week, 2016
- "Adler After Dark", Adler Planetarium, 2015 present
- Camp Neuro Chicago, 2015